Guide to the Park Benjamin Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Park Benjamin Papers
1645-1925.
Benjamin, Park, 1809-1864.
9.24 linear ft (in 22 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079146
History
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts of poems, and manuscripts of lectures by Benjamin. The correspondence consists of original letters of Benjamin, typescript and photostatic copies of Benjamin letters in other libraries, and letters to Benjamin from some of his literary contemporaries including Paul Hamilton Hayne, Willis Gaylord Clark, John Lothrop Motley, and Fitz-Greene Halleck. Many of the letters relate to Park Benjamin's lecture tours. There are other family letters and many documents relating to the Benjamin family,and two letterbooks of John Lothrop Motley. Also, a large amount of genealogical material of the Benjamin family, and its related families from the 16th century to the present day. There are also financial records, monographs, clippings, and photographs.
Arrangement
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged. Box 1-4: Cataloged correspondence; Box 5-6: Cataloged manuscripts & documents; Box 7-8: Poems; Box 9: Lectures; Box 10-11: Genealogical materials; Box 12: Demerara accounts; Box 13: Photographs & sheet music; Box 13-15: Printed materials; Box 16: Benjamin family items; Box 17-22: Merle Hoover notes.
Subjects
Adams, John Quincy, 1787-1848.; Argyll, George Douglas Campbell, Duke of, 1823-1900.; Arthur, T. S. (Timothy Shay), 1809-1885.; Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss, 1816-1894.; Barnard, Henry, 1811-1900.; Beeton, Samuel Orchart, 1831-1877.; Benjamin, John, 1598-1645.; Benjamin, Park, 1849-1922.; Benjamin family.; Berington, Joseph, 1746-1827.; Bright, John, 1811-1889.; Brooks, N. C. (Nathan Covington), 1809-1898.; Caruso, Enrico, 1873-1921.; Chester, Joseph Lemuel, 1821-1882.; Child, Lydia Maria, 1802-1880.; Clark, Lewis Gaylord, 1808-1873.; Clark, Willis Gaylord, 1808-1841.; Clemens, Olivia Langdon, 1845-1904.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910.; Cooke, John Esten, 1830-1886.; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.; Dix, John Ross, 1800?-1885.; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865.; Ferris, Morris Patterson, Mrs., 1855-1932.; Forster, W. E. (William Edward), 1818-1886.; Foster, Lafayette S. (Lafayette Sabine), 1806-1880.; Gramont, Antoine Alfred Agénor de, Duc de Gramont & de Guiche, 1819-1880.; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872.; Greenwood, Grace, 1823-1904.; Grinnell, Moses Hicks, 1803-1877.; Griswold, Rufus W. (Rufus Wilmot), 1815-1857.; Guizot, M. (François), 1787-1874.; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.; Hale, Sarah Josepha Buell, 1788-1879.; Halleck, Fitz-Greene, 1790-1867.; Harris, Joel Chandler, 1848-1908.; Hayne, Paul Hamilton, 1830-1886.; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878.; Herbert, Henry William, 1807-1879.; Hildreth, Richard, 1807-1885.; Hillard, George Stillman, 1808-1879.; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.; Judson, Emily C. (Emily Chubbuck), 1817-1854.; Kennedy, John Pendleton, 1795-1870.; Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862.; Körner, Gustav Philipp, 1809-1896.; Lanman, James, 1767-1841.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Lossing, Benson John, 1813-1891.; Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton, Earl of, 1831-1891.; Madison, James, 1751-1836.; Marsh, George Perkins, 1801-1882.; Mitchill, Samuel L. (Samuel Latham), 1784-1831.; Morris, George Pope, 1802-1864.; Motley, John Lothrop, 1814-1877.; Motley, Thomas.; Neal, John, 1793-1876.; Otis, George A. (George Alexander), 1830-1881.; Park, Moses, 1738-1828.; Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849.; Quincy, Josiah, 1802-1882.; Randall, Samuel, 1778-1864.; Raymond, Henry J. (Henry Jarvis), 1820-1869.; Routledge, George, 1812-1888.; Sargent, Epes, 1813-1880.; Savage, James, 1784-1873.; Savage, William, 1779-1851.; Senior, Nassau William, 1790-1864.; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872.; Sheridan, Mary Motley.; Sherwood, M. E. W. (Mary Elizabeth Wilson), 1826-1903.; Sigourney, L. H. (Lydia Howard), 1791-1865.; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866.; Spencer, John C. (John Canfield), 1788-1855.; Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1814-1889.; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908.; Stephens, Ann S. (Ann Sophia), 1810-1886.; Studley, S. C.,--Mrs.; Stuyvesant, Peter, 1592-1672.; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874.; Sutherland, Harriet Elizabeth Georgiana Howard Leveson-Gower, Duchess of, 1808-1868.; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1844-1919.; Verplanck, Gulian C. (Gulian Crommelin), 1786-1870.; Warner, Charles Dudley, 1829-1900.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; Welles, Gideon, 1802-1878.; Willis, Nathaniel Parker, 1806-1867.; Whipple, Edwin Percy, 1819-1886.; Wright, Frances, 1795-1852.; Demerara.; Norwich (Conn.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Foreign public opinion, Austrian.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Foreign public opinion, British.; African Americans--History--19th century.; American literature--19th century.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--19th century.; Plantations--Guyana--19th century.; Publishers and publishing--19th century.; Account books.; Accounts.; Advertising.; Albums.; Bank drafts.; Bills of sale.; Biographies.; Bonds.; Certificates.; Commissions.; Deeds.; Diaries.; Drawings.; Essays.; Estate inventories.; Financial records.; Genealogies.; Indentures.; Ink drawings.; Inventories.; Invoices.; Lectures.; Letterbooks.; Lists.; Mortgages.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Payrolls.; Photographs.; Poems.; Portraits.; Powers of attorney.; Receipts.; Resolutions.; Scores.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Stock certificates.; Tickets.; Wills.; Authors, American--19th century.; Diplomats.; Historians.; Journalists.; Plantation owners.; Poets.; Slaveholders.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
The following boxes are located off-site: 7-22. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room. This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
03/--/1937 M37-03 Benjamin, W. E. Gift
01/26/1994 M-94-01-26 Letterbook of J.L. Motley 5285B (NYState) Purchase
05/20/1994 M-94-05-20 A. Lincoln letter Pratt, Dallas Bequest
Gift of William E. Benjamin, 1937; added to by gifts from his family.
Bequest of Dallas Pratt, 1994.
Finding aid available in repository and online.
- Series I: Cataloged Materials
  - Subseries I.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - Adams, John Quincy (Box 1)
    - Albouy, James H. (Box 1)
    - Aldrich, James (Box 1)
    - Arthur, Timothy Shay (Box 1)
    - Barnard, Henry (Box 1)
    - Benjamin, A. (Box 1)
    - Benjamin, Benjamin Henry (Box 1)
    - Benjamin, George H. (Box 1)
    - Benjamin, Mary Brower Western (Box 1)
    - Benjamin, Park
      - Through 1842 (Box 1)
      - 1843-1853 (Box 2)
      - 1854-1864 (Box 3)
    - Benjamin, Walter Romeyn (Box 3)
    - Benjamin, William Christopher (Box 3)
    - Benjamin, William Evarts (Box 3)
    - Berington, Joseph (Box 3)
    - Blount, John P. (Box 3)
    - Bowe, O.A. (Box 4)
    - Braggins, Mary Ann (Box 4)
    - Brooks, N.C. (Box 4)
    - Burbeck, Henry (Box 4)
    - Caruso, Enrico (Box 4)
    - Child, Lydia Maria (Box 4)
    - Clark, Lewis Gaylord (Box 4)
    - Clark, Willis Gaylord (Box 4)
    - Clemens, Olivia Langdon (Box 4)
    - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne (Box 4)
    - Cooke, John Esten (Box 4)
    - Croswell, William (Box 4)
    - Curtis, George William (Box 4)
    - D'Arusmont, Frances Wright (Box 4)
    - Davenport, F. Gladys (Box 4)
    - Dix, J. R. (Box 4)
    - Emmott, Mary Gertrude Lees (Box 4)
    - Everett, Edward (Box 4)
    - Ferris, Mary L.D. (Box 4)
    - Foster, Lafayette S. (Box 4)
    - Goddard, Calvin (Box 4)
    - Greeley, Horace (Box 4)
    - Griswold, Rufus Wilmot (Box 4)
    - Hale, Edward Everett (Box 4)
    - Hale, Sara Josepha (Box 4)
    - Halleck, Fitz-Greene (Box 4)
    - Harcourt, Elizabeth Motley Ives (Box 4)
    - Hayne, Paul Hamilton (Box 4)
    - Henry, Joseph (Box 4)
    - Herbert, Henry William (Box 4)
    - Hillard, George Stillman (Box 4)
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell (Box 4)
    - Ingersoill, R.J. (Box 4)
    - Jefferson, Thomas (Box 4)
    - Judson, Emily C. "Fanny Forester" (Box 4)
    - Kennedy, John P. (Box 4)
    - Knowles, James Sheridan (Box 4)
    - Lanman, James (Box 4)
    - Lanman, Mary Judith Gall Benjamin (Box 4)
    - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 4)
    - Lippincott, Sara Hame (Grace Greenwood) (Box 4)
    - Lossing, Benson J. (Box 4)
    - Madison, James (Box 4)
    - Marsh, George P. (Box 4)
    - MildMay, Herbert St. John- (Box 4)
    - MildMay, Susan Motley St. John (Mrs. Herbert) (Box 4)
    - Mitchill, Samuel Latham (Box 4)
    - Morris, George P. (Box 4)
    - Motley, John Lothrop (Box 4)
    - Motley, Mary Elizabeth Benjamin (Mrs. John Lothrop) (Box 4)
    - Neal, John (Box 4)
    - Poe, Edgar Allan (Box 4)
    - Raymond, Henry J. (Box 4)
    - Roberts, Dwight (Box 4)
    - Romaine, Benj amin (Box 4)
    - Romaine, Samuel B. (Box 4)
    - Romaine, Thomas (Box 4)
    - Romeyn, Joanna B. (Box 4)
    - Russell, Henry (Box 4)
    - Sargent, Epes (Box 4)
    - Sargent, John O. (Box 4)
    - Savage, James (Box 4)
    - Savage, William (Box 4)
    - Sheridan, Mary Motley (Mrs. Algernon Brinsley) (Box 4)
    - Sigourney, Lydia Howard Huntley (Mrs. Charles) (Box 4)
    - Sparks, Jared (Box 4)
    - Spencer, John C. (Box 4)
    - Stackpole, Joseph Lewis (Box 4)
    - Stephens, Ann S. (Box 4)
    - Strong, Henry (Box 4)
    - Studley, Sarah C. (Box 4)
    - Tappan, Francis W. (Box 4)
    - Tasistro, L. Fitzgerald (Box 4)
    - Treat, Lilian Benjamin (Box 4)
    - Trumbull, Jonathan (Box 4)
    - Verplanck, Gulian C. (Box 4)
    - Washington, George (Box 4)
    - Whipple, E. P. (Box 4)
    - Willia, Nathaniel Parker (Box 4)
    - Willis, Nathaniel (Box 4)
    - Witter, John (Box 4)
    - Yates, Francis (Box 4)
  - Suberies I.2: Cataloged Manuscripts and Documents
    - Benjamin, Aaron (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, Benjamin Henry (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, Charles (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, David (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, George (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, John (1598-1645) (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, John (1682-1716) (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, John (1714-1787) (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, Joseph (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, Park (1770-1824) (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, Park (1809-1864) (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, Park (1849-1922) (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, Phebe Larrabee (Box 5)
    - Benjamin, William Evarts (Box 5)
    - Braggins, Mary Ann (Box 5)
    - Brower, Everardus (Box 5)
    - Brower, John (Box 5)
    - Caruso, Enrico (Box 5)
    - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne (Box 5)
    - Cunningham, James (Box 5)
    - De Joust, Edward (Box 5)
    - Harcourt, Elizabeth Motley Ives (Box 5)
    - Harris, Joel Chandler (Box 5)
    - Landry, Thomas (Box 5)
    - Lanman, Mary Judith Gall Benjamin (Box 5)
    - Loux, James B. (Box 5)
    - Motley, John Lothrop (Box 6)
      - Letterbook, 1847-1857
        (Boston. 1 vol., 38pp. Copies of 18 letters, addressed to persons named below.)
        - George Atkinson (3) (Box 6)
        - Park Benjamin, 1809-1864 (4) (Box 6)
        - John Chapman, 1822-1894 (Box 6)
        - Joseph Green Cogswell, 1786-1871 (Box 6)
        - Frederic Prentice (3) (Box 6)
        - George Routledge, 1812-1888 (2) (Box 6)
        - John Osborne Sargent, 1811-1891 (Box 6)
        - Henry Strong (3) (Box 6)
      - Letterbook, 1861-1865
        (London and Vienna. 1 vol., 269pp. Secretatrial copies of 38 letters to the persons named below.)
        - George Douglas Campbell, 8th Duke of Argyll, 1823-1900 (Box 6)
        - Nathaniel Prentiss Banks, 1816-1894 (Box 6)
        - Samuel Orchart Beeton, 1831-1877 (Box 6)
        - John Bright, 1811-1889 (Box 6)
        - Joseph Lemuel Chester, 1821-1882 (Box 6)
        - William Edward Forster, 1818-1886 (Box 6)
        - Antoine Alfred Agenor, Duc de Gramont & de Guiche, 1819-1880 (Box 6)
        - William Gray (Box 6)
        - Moses Hicks Grinnell, 1803-1877 (2) (Box 6)
        - Francois Pierre Guillaume Guizot, 1787-1874 (Box 6)
        - Gustav Philipp Körner, 1809-1896 (Box 6)
        - __ Lengel (Box 6)
        - Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton, 1st Earl of Lytton, 1831-1891 (Box 6)
        - Major Mansfeldt (Box 6)
        - Thomas Motley, Jr. (8) (Box 6)
        - James Shepherd Pike, 1811-1882 (Box 6)
        - Publishers of Biographical Dictionaries (Box 6)
        - Messrs Routledge, Warre & Routledge (Box 6)
        - Nassau William Senior, 1790-1864 (Box 6)
        - William Henry Seward, 1801-1872 (4) (Box 6)
        - William Sharwood (Box 6)
        - Mary Elizabeth Wilson Sherwood (Mrs. John), 1826-1903 (Box 6)
        - Edwin McMasters Stanton, 1814-1869 (Box 6)
        - Charles Sumner, 1811-1874 (Box 6)
        - Harriet Elizabeth Georgiana Howard Leveson-Gower, Duchess of Sutherland, 1806-1868 (Box 6)
        - John L. Tucker (Box 6)
    - Motley, Thomas and Edward (Box 6)
    - Neal, John (Box 6)
    - Otis, George Alexander (Box 6)
    - Park, Jonathan (Box 6)
    - Park, Moses (Box 6)
    - Peck, Benjamin (Box 6)
    - Pierce family (Box 6)
    - Quincy, Josiah (Box 6)
    - Randall, Samuel (Box 6)
    - Romaine, Benjamin (Box 6)
    - Sargent, Epes (Box 6)
    - Savage, James (Box 6)
    - Sigourney, Lydia Howard Huntley (Box 6)
    - Stedman, Edmund Clarence (Box 6)
    - Stuyvesant, Petrus (Box 6)
    - Warner, Charles Dudley (Box 6)
    - Washington, George (Box 6)
    - Washington College Parthenon (Box 6)
    - Welles, Gideon (Box 6)
    - Western, Henry Membrey (Box 6)
    - Western, Thomas (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Series II: Uncataloged Papers
  - Poems (Box 6)
  - Lectures (Box 7-8)
  - Genealogical Materials (Box 9)
    (Collected by W.E. Benjamin, with notes by Merle Hoover)
  - Demerara Accounts (Box 10-11)
    (Financial records of the Benjamin properties in British Guiana)
  - Photographs (Box 12)
  - Sheet Music with lyrics by P. Benjamin (Box 12)
  - Printed Materials (Box 13)
  - Benjamin Family (Box 13-15)
    (Items related to Park Benjamin, Jr., Gladys Benjamin Goddard, Dorothy Benjamin Caruso, and Enrico Caruso. Gift of the Estate of Gladys Benjamin Goddard, 1976)
  - Merle Hoover (Box 16)
    - Merle Hoover Notes (Box 17-21)
    - Merle Hoover Biography--Notes (Box 22)